<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://iemprog.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://iemprog.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-10-13T13:15:46+00:00</updated><id>https://iemprog.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>Personal website and blog of Imad Eddine Marouf - PhD student in Machine Learning and Continual Learning. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">How to Stop Guessing and Start Building Products People Actually Want</title><link href="https://iemprog.github.io/blog/2024/StopGuessingAndBuildProducts/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to Stop Guessing and Start Building Products People Actually Want"/><published>2024-06-18T10:40:15+00:00</published><updated>2024-06-18T10:40:15+00:00</updated><id>https://iemprog.github.io/blog/2024/StopGuessingAndBuildProducts</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://iemprog.github.io/blog/2024/StopGuessingAndBuildProducts/"><![CDATA[<p>You’ve got a million-dollar idea. A SaaS product poised to revolutionize an industry. But how do you know it’s not just a pipe dream? The answer, as outlined in Rob Fitzpatrick’s insightful book “The Mom Test,” lies in talking to potential customers, but not in the way you think. Forget the generic “Would you buy this?” questions. As business creator, you have to master The Mom Test, a revolutionary approach to customer conversations that’ll separate the gold from the fool’s gold.</p> <p>In this article, I’ll distill the key ideas I’ve learned from Fitzpatrick’s work, and show you how to uncover the hidden truths about your product’s potential.</p> <p>The Mom Test isn’t about finding validation; it’s about unearthing the truth. It’s about understanding the real problems your potential customers face, the solutions they’ve already tried, and what they’d be willing to pay for something better. Think of it as a detective’s toolkit for uncovering the hidden desires and frustrations that drive your target market</p> <p>Forget the generics, embrace the specifics:</p> <p>Imagine you’re building a software to streamline the hiring process for small businesses. Instead of asking “Do you struggle with finding the right candidates?”, you dive deeper with “Tell me about the last time you hired someone. What were the biggest challenges you faced? What tools did you use? What frustrated you the most?”</p> <p>The Mom Test is all about real-life examples. It’s about digging into their past experiences, extracting concrete data about their pain points, their current solutions (even if they’re inefficient), and their hopes for a better way.</p> <p>Listen, don’t lecture:</p> <p>You’re not there to sell, you’re there to learn. Let your customers lead the conversation. Ask questions that steer them towards their problems, their goals, and their current workflows. You might discover a whole new set of needs and frustrations that you never even considered.</p> <p>The Mom Test rules:</p> <p>Talk about their life, not your idea: Focus on their problems, their goals, and their daily challenges. Don’t get lost in the excitement of your own vision.</p> <p>Focus on the past, not opinions about the future: “Always” and “would” are dangerous words. Get specific details about real-life situations. “How did you handle that situation last week?” is much more valuable than “Would you use this tool?”</p> <p>Listen more, talk less: You’ll learn more by being silent than by trying to impress.</p> <p>Unmasking the “Why” behind feature requests:</p> <p>When someone throws out a feature request, don’t just add it to your to-do list. Dig deeper! Ask, “Why do you want that? What would it let you do? How are you coping without it?” You might find that the feature isn’t as important as it initially seemed, or that there’s a bigger underlying problem that needs to be addressed.</p> <p>Emotional signals are goldmines:</p> <p>Pay attention to your customers’ body language and tone. If they get particularly excited or frustrated about a specific problem, that’s where the real pain lies. Ask them to elaborate, dig deeper, and uncover the root of their emotions. Use phrases like:</p> <p>“Tell me more about that.”</p> <p>“That seems to really bug you — I bet there’s a story here.”</p> <p>“What makes it so awful?”</p> <p>“Why haven’t you been able to fix this already?”</p> <p>Don’t be afraid to ask the “destroy-your-business” question. This means asking questions that could potentially invalidate your idea, but could also lead to invaluable insights:</p> <p>“Do you think we should push back the launch add that feature, or is it something we could add later?”</p> <p>“How would that fit into your day?”</p> <p>The Mom Test Thumb Rules:</p> <p>You’re shooting blind until you understand their goals: Focus on their aspirations and what they’re trying to achieve.</p> <p>Watching someone do a task will show you where the problems and inefficiencies really are, not where the customer thinks they are: Observe their actual workflows and processes, not just their opinions.</p> <p>If they haven’t looked for ways of solving it already, they’re not going to look for (or buy) yours: Find out what they’ve already tried and why they’ve settled for their current solution.</p> <p>While it’s rare for someone to tell you precisely what they’ll pay you, they’ll often show you what it’s worth to them: Observe their reactions, their level of frustration, and their willingness to pay for a solution.</p> <p>People want to help you, but will rarely do so unless you give them an excuse to do so: Frame your conversations in a way that makes them feel like they’re contributing to something valuable.</p> <p>Start broad and don’t zoom in until you’ve found a strong signal, both with your whole business and with every conversation: Get a general understanding of their needs before focusing on specific features or solutions.</p> <p>Keep having conversations until you stop hearing new stuff: Don’t stop at the first few conversations; keep exploring and learning until you’ve exhausted all the key insights.</p> <p>If it feels like they’re doing you a favour by talking to you, it’s probably too formal: Keep it casual and conversational; avoid rigid interview formats.</p> <p>Give as little information as possible about your idea while still nudging the discussion in a useful direction: Focus on their needs and experiences, not your own pitch.</p> <p>The Mom Test isn’t about finding validation, it’s about finding the truth.</p> <p>And the truth, however painful it may be, is what will ultimately lead you to build a product that people will truly love and pay for.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="business"/><category term="product-development"/><category term="customer-research"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[How to Stop Guessing and Start Building Products People Actually Want The MOM Test]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Does It Make The Boat Go Faster? Focus on Speed Instead of Maintenance for Faster Results</title><link href="https://iemprog.github.io/blog/2024/DoesItMakeTheBoatGoFaster/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Does It Make The Boat Go Faster? Focus on Speed Instead of Maintenance for Faster Results"/><published>2024-06-15T10:40:15+00:00</published><updated>2024-06-15T10:40:15+00:00</updated><id>https://iemprog.github.io/blog/2024/DoesItMakeTheBoatGoFaster</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://iemprog.github.io/blog/2024/DoesItMakeTheBoatGoFaster/"><![CDATA[<p>In my previous article, “Understanding the Cause-and-Effect Timeframes: The Delayed Gratification Advantage”, we explored the powerful connection between our actions and their long-term consequences. We often focus on the immediate, the quick fix, the instant reward. But, real returns, the kind that leaves a lasting impact, isn’t built on fleeting wins. It’s about understanding that the results we see today are often the culmination of actions taken long ago. You can read the full article <a href="https://imadmarouf.substack.com/p/understanding-the-cause-and-effect">here</a>.</p> <p>This leads us to a key concept, one that builds on this idea of long-term impact: Prioritizing for speed, not just maintenance.</p> <p>Think of your business, your career, or even your personal goals as a boat. We all tend to get caught up in the day-to-day maintenance of keeping things afloat, ensuring everything is running smoothly. But, the question that truly matters is: Will it make the boat go faster?</p> <p>Olympic champion Ben Hunt-Davis asks this very question in his book “Will it make the boat go faster?”. He emphasizes that, like a rower focused on winning, we need to ruthlessly prioritize tasks that have a high impact on the outcome, rather than simply staying busy.</p> <p>This concept is a powerful reminder that true progress requires a shift in perspective. We need to move beyond the trap of constant busyness and focus on the actions that will propel us toward our goals.</p> <p>The rest of this article will explore this “speed-focused” approach in detail, providing concrete examples and actionable strategies to help you prioritize for impact and achieve faster results. Let’s dive in!</p> <p>Here’s the thing: We all get caught up in the daily grind. Emails pile up, meetings take over our days, and we’re left feeling like we’re running on a hamster wheel. But are we actually making progress, or just staying busy?</p> <p>Hunt-Davis, an Olympic champion, asks this very question in his book “Will it make the boat go faster?” He emphasizes that in any pursuit, whether it’s rowing or running a business, we need to focus on tasks that have a real impact on the outcome.</p> <p>Here’s a simple way to think about it: imagine your business is a boat. Maintenance tasks are like keeping the boat clean and in good condition. While they’re important, they won’t actually make it go faster. The tasks that do make the boat go faster are those that directly impact your performance and results.</p> <p>Think about it this way:</p> <p>Cleaning your email inbox: Feels productive, but doesn’t move the needle.</p> <p>Attending a webinar on productivity hacks: Could be helpful, but not a guarantee of success.</p> <p>Developing a killer sales funnel: Directly impacts your conversion rates and revenue.</p> <p>Streamlining your accounting and cash flow: Essential for your business’s financial health and growth.</p> <p>So how can you differentiate between these two types of tasks? Hunt-Davis suggests a three-pronged approach:</p> <p>Seek to eliminate: If a task isn’t crucial to your success, eliminate it. This might feel counterintuitive, as it often means saying “no” to requests and tasks that don’t directly contribute to your goals. But remember, it’s better to focus your energy on what matters most than to spread yourself thin.</p> <p>Seek to automate: If a task is repetitive and doesn’t require your unique skills, automate it. This could involve using software for email marketing, online scheduling, or basic bookkeeping tasks.</p> <p>Delegate the rest: For tasks that can’t be eliminated or automated, delegate to others. This means building a strong team that can handle the essential functions while you focus on strategy and growth.</p> <p>The real key to achieving your goals is not busyness, but laser-focus. This means prioritizing tasks that have a direct impact on your goals. You’ll feel more focused, energized, and ultimately, more successful.</p> <p>Here are some real-world examples to inspire you:</p> <p>A young entrepreneur decided to eliminate phone support entirely. They were spending hours each day fielding calls that often took away from their core business activities. Instead, they invested in building a robust email support system.</p> <p>The result? They freed up valuable time and energy, allowing them to focus on product development and customer acquisition. Their customer satisfaction levels also improved, as they were able to provide a more consistent and personalized email response.</p> <p>A team of marketing professionals found that they were spending a huge amount of time each week managing their social media accounts. They realized that automating their posts with scheduling tools would free them up to create more engaging and valuable content.</p> <p>This allowed them to focus on running strategic advertising campaigns and crafting compelling stories that resonated with their target audience.</p> <p>Don’t get stuck in the routines of task achievement. Always assess the importance of your tasks, and whether they help the boat move faster or not. By prioritizing for speed, you’ll be able to make significant progress and leave a lasting impact.</p> <p>So, ask yourself, “Will it make the boat go faster?” And start focusing on the tasks that will propel you toward your goals.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="sample-posts"/><category term="https://imadmarouf.substack.com/p/does-it-make-the-boat-go-faster-focus"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The Will It Make the Boat Go Faster Test: Focus on What Really Matters]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Understanding the Cause-and-Effect Timeframes: The Delayed Gratification Advantage</title><link href="https://iemprog.github.io/blog/2024/understanding/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Understanding the Cause-and-Effect Timeframes: The Delayed Gratification Advantage"/><published>2024-05-01T00:32:13+00:00</published><updated>2024-05-01T00:32:13+00:00</updated><id>https://iemprog.github.io/blog/2024/understanding</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://iemprog.github.io/blog/2024/understanding/"><![CDATA[<p>We often focus on the immediate, the quick fix, the instant reward. But, real returns, the kind that leaves a lasting impact, isn’t built on fleeting wins. It’s about understanding the powerful connection between cause and effect, and realising that the results we see today are often the culmination of actions taken long ago.</p> <p>Think of it like this:</p> <p>Imagine two graphs. One represents your memory of the work you put in, and the other represents the effects of that work.</p> <p>The memory graph starts high, because you remember what you did today. You can vividly recall that late-night brainstorming session, that intense sales call, or that long, arduous research project. It’s fresh in your mind, and you feel the effort you put in. But, as time passes, your memory fades. You might remember the general gist of what you did, but the details blur. The effort you put in feels like a distant memory. You might even start to believe that the results you’re seeing now are directly linked to the work you did yesterday, or the week before.</p> <p>The effect graph, however, starts low, and slowly climbs over time. The actions you took today might not have a noticeable impact immediately. It’s like planting a seed. You can’t expect a full-grown tree overnight. But, over time, with consistent care and attention, the seed will sprout, grow, and eventually bear fruit. The real magic happens when you realize that the fruit you’re harvesting today is the result of years of consistent effort, of planting seeds and nurturing them.</p> <p>The problem is that most people get caught up in the memory graph. They focus on the first-order consequences of their actions, the immediate results. They see a tiny sprout and think, “This isn’t working!” They’re too focused on the short-term, and they fail to see the long-term potential. They believe that the success they’re experiencing now is directly tied to the work they did yesterday, or the week before. They fail to recognize the compounding effect of their actions over time.</p> <p>This short-sightedness is even evident in children. The classic Stanford Marshmallow Experiment, also known as the Marshmallow Test, measures a child’s ability to delay gratification. Children are given a marshmallow and told they can have a second one if they wait for a set period. Some kids can’t resist the immediate reward and gobble up the marshmallow right away. Others, however, demonstrate remarkable self-control and wait for the bigger reward -for more details check the reference-.</p> <p>The experiment helps researchers understand the relationship between self-control and later-life outcomes, showing that those who could delay gratification often went on to achieve greater success in life.</p> <p>The ability to delay gratification is just one aspect of long-term thinking. It’s also about considering the second-order consequences of your actions. What will happen as a result of the immediate outcome? For example, if you take a shortcut at work, you might get your task done faster, but you might also damage your reputation or create resentment among your colleagues.</p> <p>Thinking about third-order consequences is even more important. What will be the long-term impact of the second-order effects? If you consistently take shortcuts, you might eventually lose your job or miss out on opportunities for advancement.</p> <p>Most people don’t think this way. They’re too focused on the current outcomes, the immediate rewards. They fail to see the bigger picture, the long-term consequences of their decisions.</p> <p>The real winners in life and business are those who can think beyond the immediate. They’re willing to delay gratification, they consider the second and third-order effects of their actions, and they make decisions that will benefit them in the long run.</p> <p>They’re like the gardener who patiently nurtures their seed, knowing that the rewards will come in due time.</p> <p>Take Jeff Bezos, the founder of Amazon, for example. He’s one of the best examples of a leader who thinks in terms of long-term consequences. When he was building Amazon, his company was making losses for years. People were puzzled, making fun of his strategy, and questioning his sanity. But, Bezos understood the power of compounding.</p> <p>He knew that building a strong foundation, investing in innovation, and focusing on customer satisfaction would pay off in the long run. In his annual letters to investors, he consistently emphasised his long-term objectives, demonstrating his commitment to the long game. And, as we all know, his strategy paid off. Amazon is now one of the most successful companies in the world.</p> <p>So, next time you’re faced with a decision, ask yourself:</p> <p>What are the long-term consequences of this action?</p> <p>Will it help me achieve my goals?</p> <p>Will it build momentum and create lasting value?</p> <p>If the answer is yes, then you’re on the right track.</p> <p>You’re playing the long game. And, if you want to have remarkable results, the long game is the only game worth playing.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="sample-posts"/><category term="https://imadmarouf.substack.com/p/understanding-the-cause-and-effect"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The Long Game: Because Life Isn't a Sprint, It's a Marathon (With Some Amazing Views Along the Way)]]></summary></entry></feed>